okay so here's the term skill stack this
is where it came from uh when I was at
IBM and we're going to show you how to
make your own skills deck it's not that
hard how to make one and how to track it
um a skills deck is just a way of
knowing what you should learn so we
recently did a video about knowing the
activities you want what jobs have those
activities what employers you know hire
for that and what are the specific you
know um quintessential skills that you
need to get that job and then start
writing down what those employers have
to tell you what are the titles what are
the you know all of the terms and
everything and that part can be a little
bit overwhelming because you're like man
they're talking about all this stuff
right well if you've already asked them
the thing what is the one most important
thing you've already started your skill
stack right that's the first item the
first line item in your skill stack so
I'm going to describe an activity that I
came up with um kind of accidentally
when I was trying to do a job change and
I'll tell you a little story about that
so when when I was at IBM I at one point
in my career I realized that my career
was kind of happening to me instead of
me controlling the career um I think
that happens to everybody at a certain
point um and you know I was I was uh you
know I was writing I was I was doing
third level support for software that
tattletail on you know whether they were
paying not enough for TI software I
hated it I absolutely hated it I was
like okay I'm going to go get another
job um and I started interviewing and
kind of funny failure that I had I
actually interviewed for an educational
job it was a it was creating educational
software uh primarily web stuff and I
had been employed I was like Web Master
for God's sake so I thought okay this
will be no problem but I hadn't been
keeping my skills up for what 10 years
or so so I mean it had I mean I'd
written JavaScript I'd written
livescript you know before many of these
people that ultimately interviewed me
had even been born but it didn't matter
so I went into this job interview and
it's kind of embarrassing but I wanted
to do this job it was one of these live
things right show us a thing it was a
little bit of a lead Cody thing not
really it was mostly just to get a sense
of it and they said we'll start with
something simple uh show us how you
parse Json and I did not know json.
parse I knew it existed I didn't I've
never used it I wrote mostly Pearl and C
uh you know my entire career um and so I
told the guy I knew I could do it but I
I didn't so I ended up writing a regular
expression Json parser in Pearl and this
this you know young person who kind of
annoyed me at the time says well so do
you think there's a simpler way and and
they the way they talk down to me I
wanted to reach through that phone or
that whatever that thing the internet
was and just slapped that kid I was so
pissed I mean this this this little
pipsqueak who was like in diapers when I
was building the freaking internet
literally through two internet service
providers was at was talking down to me
about parsing
Json and I did not like that I did not
like that I was so mad and and you know
what sometimes that kind of you need an
you need an experience like that I
wasn't mad at him but he was the
messenger and the message was hey old
man you have forgotten to keep your
skills stack up to date that was the
message and he just happened to be the
messenger so obviously I didn't get it
the recruiter that I had interviewed
with that got me the position he says
well they really like you they like your
energy and experience but you know they
just want you to come back once you have
more of the basic skills that they need
I went oh my God okay and I knew better
but my hubis had made me had made it
think that oh hey I could go into these
jobs and get it no matter what just
because you know I can do anything I can
learn anything fast enough and I can I
can learn pretty much any so I
immediately set forward to never ever
have that happen again and that that is
when I built my first skill stack and
all I did is I took a piece of paper at
the time I started making a little app
for it uh but you don't need that you
just need a piece of paper with three
colums really that's it maybe just two
columns three columns and the one column
um uh the one column is just reference
points acronyms titles of languages
Concepts you know all the stuff that
you're going to think that you're going
to hear
about and um the you know and then the
the middle column is going to be a
number it's going to be a ranking and
then the third column now I've actually
done this video already so I'm having a
hard time because I'm redoing the same
thing so um I'm but I'm gonna go ahead
and tell you so to to do a skill stack
is very simple you you you start
remember that whole thing about writing
that number one thing that's going to
help you get the job from your employer
the potential employer that you asked
put that down in my case it would have
been Pearl right and then I would have
given myself a rank in the First Column
and I'm using actually interviewed for a
Google job and they gave me their
ranking system let me tell you this
ranking system really quickly which I
also already did in another video but
I'm G do it again so zero is I have no
idea what it is somebody said this thing
and I need to know what it is I have no
idea uh one is I know what it is I can
tell you what it is but I have no idea
how to use it or do it uh two is I it's
kind of an experimental knowledge I'm
messing around with it I'm sort of
dangerous you know I know what's up but
I I could tell you about it enough and I
could kind of have a sense of it three
means that I could be gainfully employed
doing it that means I have the minimum
necessary skill to meet the needs of any
job that required that thing right um
four is um four it means that you are
kind of theem you're the subject matter
expert on the topic with your group uh
you know your localized group um of you
know your team they come to you when
they have a question about Pearl for
example um you know my case I'm that way
on my team for go I am definitely the on
my team for go I have the most
experience in it uh among the the 12
people on my team or so um and they they
regularly come to me to bounce ideas and
make sure that I am the one who reviews
the stuff so and then beyond that is a
is a five and a five means that you have
kind of larger scope so outside of your
immediate team not only you're the team
expert but you know you're giving
conferences internally within your
company uh you're regularly being asked
to to present in meetups um and
everything above that from six to 10 10
being I invented it I am Larry wall I
invented Pearl in that case you know um
and again this is Google who made this
and then but six would mean you know I'm
regularly doing conference presentations
and I'm gain fully employed doing this
people pay me a lot of money to to
assign Direction seven would be
something like I'm on the board you know
I help make you know directional
decisions on the go for the go team I
regular you know core contributor uh
again eight nine it's all different
levels of you know real solid mastering
organization and Leadership at the level
of uh above five so most of us will
never get above five in most of the
things that we need to do um and and but
our goal should be a three we should
definitely be a three in anything that
we that someone tells us we need to
learn to get the job right now the
reason that we're having a column here
is because you're going to you're going
to hear about things that you're you're
going to hear about them it's going to
make you very uncomfortable you're going
to be like I don't know what that is so
in order to Not freak out write it down
anyway and then you may come back once
you learn what it is go well that has
nothing to do with what I want to do in
my job or anything then you put you put
you know where you're at so you're a
zero now you're a one right because you
know what it is so you just write it
down you write a zero and then you
figure out what it is you make yourself
a one and then but but this here's where
the third column comes in the more that
you get into you know knowing about your
employer and the key skills so there's
that one skill that you asked your
employer remember you said what is the
one thing that I need to learn to get a
job here that thing goes in column the
other column and in that specific thing
you probably want to put a five or a
three or at least a three right so in my
case in that time I'm using my example
it would be pearl and I would have had
in the in the you know there's three
columns there's you know the the title
there's there's where I am and where I
want to be or where I need to be and and
then that that last column I would put a
five because I not only that not only do
I want to be you know employable I want
to be so employable that they can't
resist me as soon as they see me and
they see my skills and I can produce the
trust they're going to be oh my God we
have to have this guy we have I don't
care how we're going to get in we have
to hire them and that's by the way
that's a really fun place to be it is so
much fun to be in that in that you know
especially if you've been you know just
begging for work for so long and but
once you become an expert when in
something it is extremely satisfying so
much so that you got to watch out
because you can become Anakin Skywalker
and that's a separate video beware of
Anakin syndrome make sure you watch that
one so that's the skill stack that's it
and once you get your skill stack done
you you just keep that piece of paper
and you just you modify it you change
your numbers based on what how you're
tweaking your job opportunities and in
my opinion you should keep two of them
circled either circled or squared um two
of the line items right and that is the
thing that you're working on currently
that you know you have to do but you
don't want to do because it's hard and
it's not as fun and the thing you know
that you have to do that's that's also
really really fun and I I like to have
two of those things you don't have to do
this but I like that because then when
you're you know strapped for motivation
um you can work with your bre best brain
power motivation on the hard thing and
then when that's that you know your
desire to work on that wains you can
fail over to the fun thing without you
know going to watch a movie or something
nothing wrong with relaxing but that's
what I like about having you know
there's always two things and the really
great thing about having your own little
paper based skill stack app is that it
really gives you Direction it makes you
feel like you know exactly what to do
and and if you feel like you've gotten
that one specific line item to where it
needs to be find the next line item you
know what I mean you don't you you're
you're you're not being inundated with a
huge you know collection of all the
things that you need to learn in this
job listing you are just focused you're
totally focused on that one thing and
the other fun thing or whatever one or
two things at a time and and when you do
that it will work and you will you will
master that thing you'll produce
evidence of that Mastery and we'll talk
about how to do all that through the
Boost but but that that is how you get
the job because you're now focused on
the things that are you know what the
job it takes you know what the specific
skills are that you need to build and
you're tracking your skill stack in a
way that is manageable and approachable
that means it's not overwhelming you if
if there's so much to learn and Tech
that if you don't do this and and this
happened to me because I was like I was
trying to get back into Tech and I was
like well damn I don't know Json very
well do I really need to learn it and so
I started just you know writing
everything down just to get it out of my
head and then I could go back and
evaluate whether I needed it or not um
so that is
uh that's how you track your own skill
stack it's also the name um that's also
the the um uh the name of the company uh
skill stack SK i l st- a k that's where
that came from um and that's you know
it's the basis of the entire boost we
are going to be specifically helping you
put blocks into your stack uh for most
of the rest of the Boost but but
starting out with the stack and having
you manage your own is an important part
of the beginning beginning of this whole
thing